Okay. You want to finish the Bodhisattva
got mad at the Bodhisattva discussion?
Yes.
Okay.
We're on Lopen Denyi.
Okay, good.
Lopen Denyi Kye Yulten La Selkama
Zekyang. Okay, those two Acharyas, okay,
those two masters who are Master
Shura and Master
Shantideva, okay, those two. Shura means
bow.
And then warrior. And then uh
Shantideva, they said
uh you lose a thousand
eons of good karma if you get mad at a
at anybody, okay?
Somebody.
Then Jetsun Kapa wants more information.
He said, "What are they talking about?"
Lopen Denyi Kye Yulten La Selkama
Zekyang. Say you.
Ten.
You.
This is a very unusual use of these two
common words, okay? Yul means
like object or country and ten means
support. Yeah, exactly.
But in Vinaya
it has a special meaning. Uh it means
the person to whom you give the vow
and the master who gives the vow are
called yul and ten, okay? So he's
playing with that usage. Here it means
the person that you got mad at and the
person the maddie and the madder.
Okay? The person who got angry and the
person they got angry at. Yul is which
one?
Yeah, the person they got mad at. So ten
must be
the person who got mad. Okay, so he's
he's playing if you don't know Vinaya
language you you you don't understand
what he's saying, okay?
Yulten Selka. We should put that in the
dictionary, Adam.
Kalsang Selka. Selkame means
sel means what? Like sel.
Clear, okay? The clear Sel means clear.
Selkame means it's not exactly clear.
It's an idiom that means it's not
exactly clear, okay? So what's he
saying?
Yeah, it's not clear in Shantideva and
it's not clear in Shura uh if the person
getting mad is a Bodhisattva or the
person they're getting mad at is a
person it's not clear. Selkame.
Zek Mazekyang Kelpa Gyal Thondus Apakyi
Tsajum Pekonto Yulani, but it but I'll
tell you if you're going to lose a
hundred or a thousand eons of good karma
if you get mad at a at them the person
you got mad at should be a
Bodhisattva, okay? That's whose opinion?
Jetsun Kapa's. Come on.
You know, if if you're going to lose a
hundred
million years of good deeds or a hundred
thousand million years of good billion
then come on, it's got to be a
Bodhisattva, the person you're getting
mad at. Master Shantideva doesn't say it
directly.
Neither did Lopen Bow, but it it must
be, he says, okay?
Chowai Denyi Changsem Dangnyi Chem Bow
Shay Sum La Pakna Yulkyi Changsem La
Changsem Topche La Drowo. There are
statements that say
that which we already covered that say
that the person who has the anger should
be not only a Bodhisattva but a high
Bodhisattva, okay? The person who has
the anger, if you're going to lose a
thousand eons of good karma
or a hundred eons of good karma
they should be a pretty powerful
Bodhisattva.
Dela Pakna, okay? Dela Pakna. Pakna, you
know Jipak Tsawa?
Yeah, deductions. Dela Pakna means, you
know, extrapolating from that
making a deduction from that then
the person they get mad at should also
be a
powerful Bodhisattva, not just a normal
Bodhisattva, powerful Bodhisattva. Here
it says Changsem Topche. What's Topche?
Yeah, the four powers. So Topche here
means the person that who's getting
angry should be powerful Bodhisattva and
the person they get angry at should be a
powerful Bodhisattva for there to be
such a collision of the Titanic and the
iceberg that you lose a thousand
eons of good karma, okay?
Dela Chowai Denyi Changsem Sokya Ngela
Yulani Satob Matob Nisu Yute.
Now, this is Jetsun Kapa also.
The person who gets the anger, Chowai
Ten, okay? The ten.
The person who got angry, that
Bodhisattva
is definitely Ngapa or a Soke, So
Sokewo.
A person who has not seen emptiness
directly. Okay? So Sokewo means
nor- normal person in the sense of not
special,
okay? Has not seen Pratyeka Buddha in
Sanskrit. They have they are
Okay? If the Bodhisattva is getting mad
this kind of anger
they they are powerful Bodhisattva but
they didn't see emptiness yet, okay? So
what did we learn?
If you're a Bodhisattva, have you
necessarily seen emptiness directly?
No, okay? So even from that sentence
you can learn something important in
Buddhism, okay?
You can be a person who has great
compassion who is dedicated to become a
Buddha to help the whole world
and it's not necessary that you saw
emptiness, okay?
Is it true that all people who saw
emptiness directly are Bodhisattva?
We say no, okay? No.
Like a a very intelligent scientist who
who doesn't really care about saving the
world
can can understand that that things are
coming from them, okay? People who
under- Heisenberg and certainty
principle. If you study it carefully
certain atomic physicists have have come
close to emptiness, okay? But they have
no intention of like saving the world
with it, okay?
Okay. So Makyewa Ichway.
What's it mean?
If you're a Bodhisattva, it doesn't
necessarily mean you saw
emptiness. If you saw emptiness, it's
not necessarily true that you're
a Bodhisattva.
Is it necessarily true that if you're a
Bodhisattva on the first Bodhisattva
level that you saw emptiness?
Yeah, good. Okay, got it?
Is there anybody on any of the ten
Bodhisattva levels who didn't see
emptiness directly?
Okay, great. Wow, you guys are good.
If you reached Nirvana, have you seen
emptiness directly?
Must be. Must be.
Must be. Cannot reach Nirvana, yeah.
Okay.
Must be, yeah.
If you reached Nirvana, did you reach
Buddhahood?
Good. Okay. All right, good.
Okay.
Can you be on the Bodhisattva track and
not see emptiness directly?
Yeah, okay? On the first two paths,
okay?
We're going to talk about it with
Kamalashila, okay? Yulani Satob Matob
Nisu Yute. So as far as the person
getting angry
they are without question not someone
who saw emptiness directly, okay? If
they're going to lose that much karma.
Okay? But what do you think about the
object that they get angry at, the
Bodhisattva they get angry at?
He says
Nisu Yute.
Two two different options. What What do
you guess?
They could be an Arya or they could not
be an Arya, okay? They could be someone
who saw emptiness directly or maybe they
didn't see emptiness. The person they
got angry at, okay?
Okay.
Deta Na Changsem Topchewa Chewe Chewa La
Dang Chewe Chewa La Dang Yul Dang Ten
Dang Nyambe Nyambala Chepa Sum O.
Therefore, there are three options.
Okay? Therefore, there are three
options. In general, we're not talking a
hundred eons or a thousand eons. In
general, there's three options. Number
one
a Bodhisattva who's stronger
is the one who got angry is stronger
than the Bodhisattva that they got angry
at, okay? That's first option. Second
option?
The Bodhisattva got angry is not as
strong as the Bodhisattva that they got
angry at. Second option. What's the
third option?
Equal strength, okay? Equal
realizations, okay?
Two three options.
Deta Dambu Lani Kelpa Gyal Yul La. Which
of those three do you guess is the one
who loses a hundred eons of good karma?
I'm sorry, let me say it again.
One of the three loses a hundred. One of
the three loses a thousand.
So which one loses a hundred?
The person getting the Bodhisattva
getting angry is
more powerful.
Okay?
And the Bodhisattva they're angry at is
less powerful. That that Bodhisattva
loses a hundred eons. Okay.
If a less powerful Bodhisattva gets mad
at him,
more powerful Bodhisattva, they lose
a thousand. Okay. That's how Jetsun Kapa
explains the difference. Okay.
What happens if they're equal?
Oh, okay.
He says that's Kapa tongue
uh okay
okay
uh
You know because it means
Abhidharma, okay, or Abhidhamma
clairvoyance, okay.
But here
Jetsun Kapa uses it as evident. It is
evident. It is obvious. Okay. What's
that mean? What When he says it's
obvious that
when there's a hundred eons lost, it's a
more powerful Bodhisattva getting mad at
a less powerful Bodhisattva. When it was
a thousand eons getting lost, it must be
a less powerful Bodhisattva getting mad
at a more powerful Bodhisattva. It's
obvious. What What's he mean?
He's deducing. He wants to alert you
that this is his opinion.
Okay. It It's apparent.
Okay. He says it's apparent. When Jetsun
Kapa says apparent, he means that's my
opinion. Okay.
You can say it seems clear. You see what
I mean? When you say that, it means
you're not sure.
It seems clear that the person who stole
the cookies out of the tin was Geshe
Michael.
When you say seems clear, it means
you're kind of letting people know that
it's your own estimation of the
situation. Okay.
And that's how Tsong Kapa warns his
readers
that this is his opinion. Okay.
He's careful to say this is my opinion.
Uh
What happens in the in the
Let me check this out.
Uh so when you say good karma is
destroyed, then it could refer to the
second or third combinations.
And even the second combination, it
depends on the relative power of the two
people, he says.
Then he says
uh if you really want to figure out how
much karma you're going to lose, okay.
Okay.
What's lung?
Lung here means scripture.
Okay. Like when you give a lung or
something, okay. So lung
you should use scripture.
Chepa chao.
This is when a high lama was to say uh
it's debatable. They say you should
check.
Chepa chao.
It's something that people have to
figure out. Okay. When Jetsun Kapa says
it, you're you're you're hope it's
hopeless.
When he says it's something we have to
figure out,
he means, you know, if if later on
people have access to more scriptures,
maybe you can get more detail, but this
is what I know.
Chepa chao means, you know,
if if if someone comes across more
scriptures, if John Brady goes to
Mongolia and finds more scriptures,
maybe we we'll have a better decision,
but based on what we have,
uh this is what it is. Okay.
Um
Remember before we had this thing about
uh you go to a billion planets and you
beat everybody up?
And it doesn't damage the Bodhisattva.
But if the Bodhisattva gets mad at
another Bodhisattva or something, then
there's damage done and they have to put
their armor back on. Okay, he wants to
go into that. He wants to explain that.
So up above when they said
any particular Bodhisattva,
there will be damage to the Bodhisattva,
he's talking about a Bodhisattva who
gets angry in their mind at someone who
is not yet a Bodhisattva
and says bad things to them and beats
them up.
When they go to the planets, when they
go to other planets, a billion planets.
Okay.
He's talking a Bodhisattva beating up
all the non-Bodhisattvas on a billion
planets. Okay.
It would not damage the Bodhisattva.
Okay. So what does damage mean? Okay.
Uh
So he's trying to just draw distinction
between a Bodhisattva who gets in a
little bit of trouble and a Bodhisattva
who gets in a lot of trouble. Okay.
So the Bodhisattva who gets in a little
bit of trouble is hurt.
Just beating up a billion people.
And then the Bodhisattva who gets angry,
uh okay, they do damage to another
Bodhisattva. They get damaged. And then
they have to put on their armor again.
So he wants to go into that. He wants to
explain what that means. It's important.
Uh it will make your life a lot easier.
You will understand more when we cover
this. Okay.
We'll try to finish tonight.
When a Bodhisattva
gets
angry in their heart at a Bodhisattva
but doesn't say anything and doesn't do
anything. Okay. Just in their heart,
they are angry at the other Bodhisattva.
Just that
just that Kapa na.
However
many However many moments of anger come
up in their heart, that many eons they
lose uh sorry.
That many eons they must put on their
armor again. Okay.
So we want to know what
What do you mean when you say they have
to put on their armor? Okay.
Bodhisattvas can beat up all the people
on a billion worlds. It doesn't damage
the Bodhisattva so much.
One Bodhisattva gets angry at another
Bodhisattva for one second.
Every moment, they lose a hundred eons
of good karma. Why? Uh sorry.
They have to spend another eon for every
moment they're angry putting on their
armor. So what does it mean? Okay.
Oh my gosh.
He's going to go off on another thing.
I'm sorry. It's late. Maybe we should do
this tomorrow. I don't know.
We might die tonight.
He says it's apparent. What's that mean?
Okay, this is my opinion. It's apparent
that
the person that you're getting angered
toward
is a Bodhisattva who has not attained
their confirmation. Okay. So I don't
know. When I was a kid
in the Christian church,
when you're sixteen years old,
when you're a baby, you get water on
your head and you become a Christian.
You don't have to do anything. You just
cry.
And then uh
But when you reach like sixteen, you
have to study the teaching of the
church. Then there's a ceremony. If you
pass the examination, there's a
ceremony. And then it's called confirm.
Like, okay, we certify you're real
Christian. Okay. Now you're old enough.
You understand the ideas.
So it's called confirmation. We have in
Buddhism also.
It's called lung temba. What's it mean?
Do you know?
Yeah, it means you have enough good
karma by now that if a Buddha walked in
here, they could say
December 3rd, 2024,
you're Buddha.
Okay. Like you reached enough good karma
that Buddha can look inside of you
and and it's funny. They usually do it
by putting their foot on your head, but
we won't do that.
Okay.
They put your foot on your head or
something like that. Okay. And they look
in your karma. They look at your karma
and they say, "Okay.
December 3rd, 2024." They can give you a
date. Some people most people are not
good enough yet to get that
confirmation.
They say, "Tell me when I become a
Buddha." Buddha goes,
"Uh still not clear."
Like, you know, maybe you're going to
mess up next year or maybe not. I don't
I can't tell yet. Okay. Okay. So that
means confirmation.
Here it says the person
who
you're angry at is not confirmed yet,
but the Bodhisattva feeling the anger,
I'm sorry.
I'm sorry. The Bodhisattva you're angry
at did get confirmed,
but the Bodhisattva who's angry did not
get confirmed yet. Okay. Then he goes
off on some project of Bolometry
Bolometry though.
Sutra, okay, to prove it.
Sorry.
Okay, this is not too long.
Uh
Long
Long ten master chanting Sambhogakaya
key a a Bodhisattva who is not confirmed
yet. Long ten top of the center gets
angry at a Bodhisattva who does have
their date fixed already, okay? What do
you call there?
They call that in the coming out the
the girl wears a gown and
Yeah, debutante. They didn't get their
debutante date. Long ten top of the
center if they get angry, okay?
If the Bodhisattva who doesn't have
their date yet gets angry at a
Bodhisattva who does have their date Sem
du Sem che na
Tawa kid then Sem gye che tsi gye ne pa
however many moments of anger they feel
De ne kalpa shi ne go cha go go goes
they will have to do one eon of new
armor.
So it's getting interesting. What does
the armor mean, okay? What does the
armor mean, okay? We don't know.
He's going to tell us.
Shi ne go cha go cha go go pa shi ne say
shi ne
Say shi ne.
Shi ne.
What's shi ne?
Shamatha, good, okay. Shi ne
is almost spelled the same. The second
syllable is low tone, okay? That's the
only difference. Shamatha is shi ne.
And shi ne means finally
okay? So like you ask your
attendant for an orange juice
in the morning and it it comes in the
afternoon.
And
you say shi ne. Oh, yeah, finally.
Okay, shi ne. That did not happen to me.
I'm just it's just an example.
I got it like 10 seconds later. I got a
whole bowlful.
Okay.
Uh okay. So shi ne means
then they're going to Here it means
they're going to have to start over
again.
Okay? Shi ne means
they're going to have to start over
again with their armor. So what's that
mean?
Perna chang sem gye tso long chem po ne
nyur por jor lam du po tu pa chi ki
if a certain Bodhisattva
was at the last stages
of the first of the five paths, okay?
Collection, right? If they were at the
last pages of stages of the first of the
five paths and they were about to reach
the second stage. What happens at the
second stage? What happens at the first
stage?
You have a good
disaster in your life, okay? It makes
you spiritual.
Okay? Disasters are very good.
Okay? That's the first We're going to
talk about it in common speech though.
The first of the five paths, okay?
Is uh you have a big problem in your
life, you become spiritual. Your mother
dies in your arms, you know? Your
brother shoots himself in the head.
Okay? Then suddenly you're like, oh,
life is
different than I thought. It's not just
rock and roll.
Okay?
That's the first path. Then so and then
the second path some basically in the
second path somebody explains to you
the pen.
Okay? When you get far enough in the
second path you cannot
you cannot go to a lower realm after you
die.
So don't complain when I explain the
pen. There was some French guy in
Singapore. I don't know his name. He
irritated me.
He said, "Why you always talk about this
pen? Every time you come to Singapore
you talk about this pen."
You know?
I'm like, "I'm trying to keep you out of
hell realms, okay?"
Shi ne go cha Sometimes a lama does
something you don't know why. Maybe they
know something.
Okay.
Shi ne go cha go go pa ni
So what does it mean they have to So
this Bodhisattva this person this
Bodhisattva was ready to go from path
one to path two very soon very soon, but
he got angry at another Bodhisattva.
Okay? Becoming clearer now, okay?
Tu pa po tu pa po You know poa, right?
Move your consciousness after death, but
it means
it literally means graduate. They were
ready to go up from path
one to path two. They were In the next
few days they were going to go from path
one to path two, but
Long ten top of the center he got mad at
his Bodhisattva who had their date
already from the Buddha. They already
got their date fixed, okay?
He got mad. So Jetsun Kapa is pulling
from different sutras to give us a clear
answer.
It's hard, but it's clear.
Okay?
If you give up cuz it's hard, I can't
help you.
You shouldn't come to these classes,
okay? You want something easy, go
somewhere else.
Okay? It's hard, but it's true, okay?
That other Bodhisattva has to be one who
is so far ahead that Buddha Buddha or
some lama gave them their date already,
okay? Who can see the future?
Okay? Chem po la nyur por tob tu ne
tob tu la tsun ne tso sem gye chang de
nyi kyi kalpa for as many instances of
anger they have. Now he doesn't say
moment, he says instances of anger,
okay? Maybe it means you have
and we debate that in the monastery, but
it means sustained anger. Like not just
like I hate you. It's got to be like for
a couple hours or something, okay? Like
you're really angry for a couple hours.
It has to be sustained anger.
Uh
as many instances of sustained anger
they have, you know, like
strong anger they don't give it up for a
couple hours or something like that.
Chang sem kyi kalpa jor lam du po mi
nyur por they will not be able to move
to the second path.
For that many eons.
Okay? Okay?
Somebody was asking me Geshe la if you
can't destroy bad seeds, how can you
destroy good seeds? This is more clear.
Did he destroy his bad good seeds?
No, he just delayed his life for about
100 million years.
Okay? Understand?
Understand? Okay? He delayed
his progress, okay?
And and probably he will never know why.
Okay? Probably he won't know why for a
long time, okay?
Uh nyi kyi kalpa jor lam du po mi nyur
por he won't be able to grow up. Shi ne
You know?
Only after a long time lam la lo he has
to keep practicing the same old path for
a really long time to go somewhere he
was supposed to go next week.
Okay? He was supposed to move up next
week to the second path. He got angry at
a at a heavy Bodhisattva
and then he just delayed his career for
100 million eons. What does it mean to
put on your armor?
He's going to have to go back over again
and do that do do 100 million years of
work over again.
That's what it means to put on your
armor, okay?
It means he has to start all over again.
Okay? He goes back to In English we say
go back to square one. He has to go back
to the beginning and start over again.
He walked for a million miles.
He got angry for 5 minutes.
They took him in a helicopter
back to the beginning and said start
again.
Really, it's worse than that, okay?
Understand?
So that's the real meaning of destroy
your karma
here.
That's one of the important meanings,
okay?
If
you have to go back to the beginning,
okay?
You okay?
How many pages Oh, we're almost to the
end.
We're almost finished with Jetsun Kapa.
I have 13 minutes. I'm using it.
Okay? De la chang ju le ka gye ten de
gya se ten na la kye ten ngam sem kye pa
che pa de ngam sem kye pa chang sem kye
pa nyi nyawa ne por gyur she tu pe sum
Master Shantideva says the Buddha said
uh
if you get
angry at a Bodhisattva who is who's
being very generous, okay? In their
life.
Uh
then for every instance of anger you
have or hatred towards them for that
many eons millions of years you must
stay in the nyalwa
hell realms, okay? Now the game has
changed.
Okay? Mas Now Jetsun Kapa is not
satisfied.
He keeps throwing more things into it,
you know? It's very Tsongkhapa. You can
spend a couple I'm going to give you the
printout tonight the translation. Spend
some time with it.
You will you will discover deeper and
deeper things. That's how Tsongkhapa is,
okay?
He's not finished yet.
She chang sem la chang tu e sem kye
chang gye ne pa nyi kyi kalpa nyi wa ne
por sung la So what's what's Master
Shantideva talking about? He's not
talking about going back to the first
path and taking a million years to get
to the second path when you were
supposed to go there in one week.
Okay? Now he's talking about hell
realms. What's that about?
Okay? Kalpa member sab pe
Uh
Karma number stop it gets a jump in the
young Yola. If of course you're going to
destroy a lot of your good karma, but
also
if
a person who hasn't got their
confirmation
gets angry at a Bodhisattva who did get
their confirmation
they need to cover shiny.
To have to go back to the beginning is
as bad as going to hell.
Okay.
And then you got to start over again.
Okay. Don't need. He says actually you
could say both.
They go to hell and they delay.
Okay.
That's depressing.
Okay. Number top of Jubilee he's going
to go to another Sutra. Okay. He's going
to go to another Sutra.
It's called uh
all things in the universe crushed into
dust.
All things in the universe crushed into
dust with what? Your wisdom.
You you understand them
everything.
Okay, got it? It's a Sutra. It's a name
of a Sutra.
Number top of Jubilee
Chung way low dung keep out of mint
chicken do some do near by Shakna Namin
talk young
Okay, good.
That Sutra says
uh
there's a bad karma called giving up the
Dharma. Okay. And I've you've seen it
happen. I've seen it happen.
Some people have a bad time in a Dharma
group
and then they just give it up. They say
that's no I decided that was stupid. All
that Dharma stuff is stupid because
someone told me I didn't have a nice
dress on. They they always have some
excuse like that. Okay. I decided I
don't like this group anymore. I decided
that's a stupid teaching. Okay. What's
the karma of that?
What's the karma of that? Okay.
Uh
low dung keep out of mint chicken do
some do near by Shakna.
If you change your mind later
and for 7 years
you confess
that negative karma three times a day.
Okay?
Who said that?
Buddha. This is Sutra. Okay. This is not
some copper. This is Sutra. Buddha said
if you if you reject the Dharma. You say
I don't like that Dharma anymore. I
don't like this I don't like it, you
know.
Then for 7 years
you change your mind. You say I made a
mistake. I'm sorry.
Then for 7 years
every single day
in the morning and at noon and in the
evening you confess.
Okay. I made a mistake. Okay. What
happens?
You can clean the karma to come.
You can clean the result. You can.
You can clean it.
There's a calendar
but
that person cannot reach
the stage called
Shanti
super patience
in the second path. They cannot reach
that for 10 million years.
Okay. That Keshanti patience matter we
call mastery
that's the one where you don't have to
go to the hell anymore. You don't have
to be animal. You don't have to be
hungry ghost. You don't have to be
that's that's the level inside the pen
level
that you have to reach. Okay.
So
there's certain kind of bad karmas you
can do
and if you work really hard with the
four powers you can clean them. You
don't have to go to hell or anything
like that, but there's a second result
is a delay.
10 million years.
You can't you will not hear
anyone explain the pen. You will go to
the bathroom
when Geshe Michael explains the pen. You
will walk in back into the room when he
just finished.
No, really it happens. Okay. It happens
this week.
No, people I got to go somewhere to get
to my I have some stupid job.
What you missed I
come on. Okay.
Go to the Shak down channel long Buddha
song or so much you can. Namin top of
gear way be be chill. So so Jetsun Kapa
says and now we're finished. Okay.
So should we bother confessing?
Should we bother with four powers?
Yes and no.
Yeah. Why?
You don't have to go to hell.
Okay.
Will it fix the delay?
He says no. You can't fix it.
Okay. It doesn't matter how many times
you confess. You cannot fix it. You you
you you always be
in
in the bathroom when Geshe La gets to
the pen.
Okay. You will have this karma. Okay.
You will always walk back in when he's
asking for money again.